JOEL (J.T.) JAMES

Highly innovative senior full-stack software engineer with 7+ years of experience solving complex technical challenges and a passion for drawing insights from sports data. Eager to contribute to a team utilizing big data to anser interesting questions.

SKILLS

Frontend

Typescript | Javascript | AngularJS | Angular 2+ | Ionic | SASS | CSS | HTML

Backend

Java | Python | Node | OSGI | Perl | Spring Boot | PostgreSQL | MySQL | Microsoft SQL | Oracle SQL

Devops

Kibana | Elasticsearch | Ansible | Bamboo | Drone

Tools

Git | Docker | Portainer | Visual Studio Code | Intellij | Eclipse | Bash

WORK EXPERIENCE

SYNTECH SYSTEMS

Embedded Software Engineer | January 2017 - Current

Working remotely as an full-stack software engineer implementing critical software components across the stack

- Architected and lead a team of 4 developers through a migration from AngularJS to Angular 8 to make page load times 2-3 times faster, modernize our technical stack, and allow developers to use more modern tools (Typescript, Angular CLI, etc) to maintain the application
- Lead architecture and implementation of payment gateway (Java, Spring Boot, PostgreSQL) for processing credit card transactions from our edge devices to various payment partners, following PCI and EMV specifications
- Partnered with senior architect to lead a team of 2 developers to port a a 20+-year-old piece of software responsible for managing edge devices from C to Java so that we could improve maintainability and allow additional developers to contribute to the codebase, as the majority of our engineers are proficient in Java
- Worked alongside testing architects to stand up an ELK stack for log aggregation and data analytics which is currently being utilized in our testing environment
- Authored many testing tools, mostly written in python. Examples include simulating vehicle behavior, simulating credit card transactions, etc
- · Lead adhoc department-wide trainings on ELK stack, Python, Angular, and other job-specific duties
- Lead adhoc training sessions on internal tools to enable customer service department to better meet customer needs
- Designed an internal Angular library for abstracting advanced form creation out of HTML and into Typescript allowing our team to more quickly develop and create forms in a type-safe environment
- · As an architecture team member, mentored junior developers through code reviews and architecture reviews

ATHENAHEALTH

Developer | May 2015 - December 2016

Worked as software developer with a focus on reporting, KPI metric aggregation, and data management

- Worked alongside business partners to facilitate loading and fetching of denormalized client data for analytics purposes
- Utilized Perl and Oracle SQL to consolidate client data in a quickly accessible form
- Utilized AngularJS and Perl to create analytics interface for presenting KPIs to clients in real time
- Tuned performance of Oracle SQL queries
- Created Angular JS frontend components and unit tests to improve modularity and code quality
- Developed internal tools to streamline Agile experience: spring planning documents, backlog management tools, Slack integrations, etc
- Lead Agile Meetings (sprint reviews, retrospectives, sprint planning, daily standups, and backlog grooming)
- · Lead adhoc training sessions on Kibana, Oracle SQL performance best practices, and other job-specific duties

PROJECTS

2020 NFL INJURIES

https://joeltjames.github.io/nfllnjury.html

A short blog post investigating the rate of injuries in the NFL during the 2020 season

FANTASY FOOTBALL CHALLENGES

https://joeltjames.github.io/fantasy-football-challenges/

A Typescript/Angular application that allows for importing data from an ESPN Fantasy Football league. The data is then analyzed and the winner of the selected challenge is decided.

GOLF LIKE THE PROS: THE SWEET SPOTS AND PITFALLS AT TPC SAWGRASS

Under the supervision of Dr. Allen Lynch, from Mercer University, I worked alongside a classmate to create a web application which displayed the most and least efficient positions on the course at TPC Sawgress. We utilized a historical data set of every shot ever taken on the PGA Tour since the early 2000s.

MEAL MEMO

https://github.com/joeltjames/meal-memo

A work-in-progress Typescript/Angular/Node/Express application intended to allow for easy recipe storage, recipe search, and meal planning.

VISUALIZING ARRAYS IN ECLIPSE

https://sites.google.com/site/eclipsearrayexplorer/home

Worked alongside a professor from the Vienna University of Technology to create a plugin for the Eclipse IDE to allow for easy visualization and inspection of Arrays and other collection types. This project was performed as part of the Google Summer of Code Program in 2013. I was one of 143 students in the United States selected for this program.

EDUCATION

MERCER UNIVERSITY

Bachelor of Science - Computational Science | August 2011 - May 2015

CONTACT INFORMATION

Website: https://joeltjames.com Email: joeltjames@gmail.com

Phone: 912-614-0374